<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % aptent SYSTEM "apt.ent"> %aptent;
<!ENTITY % aptverbatiment SYSTEM "apt-verbatim.ent"> %aptverbatiment;
<!ENTITY % aptvendor SYSTEM "apt-vendor.ent"> %aptvendor;
]>

<refentry>

 <refentryinfo>
   &apt-author.team;
   &apt-email;
   &apt-product;
   <!-- The last update date -->
   <date>2016-11-20T00:00:00Z</date>
 </refentryinfo>
 
 <refmeta>
   <refentrytitle>apt</refentrytitle>
   <manvolnum>8</manvolnum>
   <refmiscinfo class="manual">APT</refmiscinfo>
 </refmeta>
 
 <!-- Man page title -->
 <refnamediv>
    <refname>apt</refname>
    <refpurpose>command-line interface</refpurpose>
 </refnamediv>

 &synopsis-command-apt;

 <refsect1><title>Description</title>
   <para><command>apt</command> provides a high-level commandline interface for
      the package management system. It is intended as an end user interface and
      enables some options better suited for interactive usage by default
      compared to more specialized APT tools like &apt-get; and &apt-cache;.
   </para><para>
   Much like <command>apt</command> itself, its manpage is intended as an end
   user interface and as such only mentions the most used commands and options
   partly to not duplicate information in multiple places and partly to avoid
   overwhelming readers with a cornucopia of options and details.
   </para>

   <variablelist>
     <varlistentry><term><option>update</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para><option>update</option> is used to download package
	   information from all configured sources. Other commands operate on
	   this data to e.g. perform package upgrades or search in and display
	   details about all packages available for installation.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>upgrade</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para><option>upgrade</option> is used to install available
	   upgrades of all packages currently installed on the system from the
	   sources configured via &sources-list;. New packages will be
	   installed if required to satisfy dependencies, but existing
	   packages will never be removed. If an upgrade for a package requires
	   the remove of an installed package the upgrade for this package
	   isn't performed.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>dist-upgrade</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>dist-upgrade</literal> in addition to performing the function of
     <literal>upgrade</literal>, also intelligently handles changing dependencies
     with new versions of packages; <command>apt-get</command> has a "smart" conflict
     resolution system, and it will attempt to upgrade the most important
     packages at the expense of less important ones if necessary.
     The <literal>dist-upgrade</literal> command may therefore remove some packages.
     The <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file contains a list of locations
     from which to retrieve desired package files.
     See also &apt-preferences; for a mechanism for
     overriding the general settings for individual packages.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>full-upgrade</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>full-upgrade</literal> performs the function of
	   upgrade but will remove currently installed packages if this is
	   needed to upgrade the system as a whole.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>install</option>, <option>remove</option>, <option>purge</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para>Performs the requested action on one or more packages
	   specified via &regex;, &glob; or exact match. The requested action
	   can be overridden for specific packages by append a plus (+) to the
	   package name to install this package or a minus (-) to remove it.
     </para><para>
	   A specific version of a package can be selected for installation by
	   following the package name with an equals (=) and the version of the
	   package to select. Alternatively the version from a specific release can be
	   selected by following the package name with a forward slash (/) and
	   codename (&debian-stable-codename;, &debian-testing-codename;, sid …) or suite name (stable,
	   testing, unstable). This will also select versions from this release
	   for dependencies of this package if needed to satisfy the request.
     </para><para>
	   Removing a package removes all packaged data, but leaves usually
	   small (modified) user configuration files behind, in case the
	   remove was an accident. Just issuing an installation request for the
	   accidentally removed package will restore its function as before in
	   that case. On the other hand you can get rid of these leftovers
	   by calling <command>purge</command> even on already removed
	   packages. Note that this does not affect any data or configuration
	   stored in your home directory.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>source</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>source</literal> causes <command>apt-get</command> to fetch source packages. APT
     will examine the available packages to decide which source package to
     fetch. It will then find and download into the current directory the
     newest available version of that source package while respecting the
     default release, set with the option <literal>APT::Default-Release</literal>,
     the <option>-t</option> option or per package with the
     <literal>pkg/release</literal> syntax, if possible.</para>

     <para>Source packages are tracked separately
     from binary packages via <literal>deb-src</literal> lines
     in the &sources-list; file. This means that you will need to add such a line
     for each repository you want to get sources from; otherwise you will probably
     get either the wrong (too old/too new) source versions or none at all.</para>

     <para>If the <option>--compile</option> option is specified
     then the package will be compiled to a binary .deb using
     <command>dpkg-buildpackage</command> for the architecture as
     defined by the <command>--host-architecture</command> option.
     If <option>--download-only</option> is specified then the source package
     will not be unpacked.</para>

     <para>A specific source version can be retrieved by postfixing the source name
     with an equals and then the version to fetch, similar to the mechanism
     used for the package files. This enables exact matching of the source
     package name and version, implicitly enabling the
     <literal>APT::Get::Only-Source</literal> option.</para>

     <para>Note that source packages are not installed and tracked in the
     <command>dpkg</command> database like binary packages; they are simply downloaded
     to the current directory, like source tarballs.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>build-dep</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>build-dep</literal> causes apt-get to install/remove packages in an
     attempt to satisfy the build dependencies for a source package. By default the dependencies are
     satisfied to build the package natively. If desired a host-architecture can be specified
     with the <option>--host-architecture</option> option instead.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>download</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
       <listitem><para><literal>download</literal> will download the given
           binary package into the current directory.
       </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>autoclean</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para>Like <literal>clean</literal>, <literal>autoclean</literal> clears out the local
     repository of retrieved package files. The difference is that it only
     removes package files that can no longer be downloaded, and are largely
     useless. This allows a cache to be maintained over a long period without
     it growing out of control. The configuration option
     <literal>APT::Clean-Installed</literal> will prevent installed packages from being
     erased if it is set to off.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>autoremove</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
     <listitem><para>
	   <literal>autoremove</literal> is used to remove packages that were
	   automatically installed to satisfy dependencies for other packages
	   and are now no longer needed as dependencies changed or the package(s)
	   needing them were removed in the meantime.
     </para><para>
	   You should check that the list does not include applications you have
	   grown to like even though they were once installed just as a
	   dependency of another package. You can mark such a package as manually
	   installed by using &apt-mark;. Packages which you have installed explicitly
	   via <command>install</command> are also never proposed for automatic removal.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>changelog</option> (&apt-get;)</term>
	<listitem><para><literal>changelog</literal> tries to download the
	      changelog of a package and displays it through
	      <command>sensible-pager</command>.  By default it
	      displays the changelog for the version that is installed.
	      However, you can specify the same options as for the
	      <option>install</option> command.</para>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>search</option> (&apt-cache;)</term>
     <listitem><para><option>search</option> can be used to search for the given
	   &regex; term(s) in the list of available packages and display
	   matches.  This can e.g. be useful if you are looking for packages
	   having a specific feature.  If you are looking for a package
	   including a specific file try &apt-file;.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>showsrc</option> (&apt-cache;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>showsrc</literal> displays all the
     source package records that match the given package names. All
     versions are shown, as well as all records that declare the name
     to be a binary package. Use <option>--only-source</option> to
     display only source package names.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>show</option> (&apt-cache;)</term>
     <listitem><para>Show information about the given package(s) including
	   its dependencies, installation and download size, sources the
	   package is available from, the description of the packages content
	   and much more. It can e.g. be helpful to look at this information
	   before allowing &apt; to remove a package or while searching for
	   new packages to install.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>depends</option> (&apt-cache;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>depends</literal> shows a listing of each dependency a package has
     and all the possible other packages that can fulfill that dependency.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>rdepends</option> (&apt-cache;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>rdepends</literal> shows a listing of each reverse dependency a
      package has.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>policy</option> (&apt-cache;)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>policy</literal> is meant to help debug issues relating to the
     preferences file. With no arguments it will print out the
     priorities of each source. Otherwise it prints out detailed information
     about the priority selection of the named package.</para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>list</option> (work-in-progress)</term>
     <listitem><para><option>list</option> is somewhat similar to <command>dpkg-query --list</command>
	   in that it can display a list of packages satisfying certain
	   criteria.  It supports &glob; patterns for matching package names as
	   well as options to list installed (<option>--installed</option>),
	   upgradeable (<option>--upgradeable</option>) or all available
	   (<option>--all-versions</option>) versions.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry><term><option>edit-sources</option> (work-in-progress)</term>
     <listitem><para><literal>edit-sources</literal> lets you edit
	   your &sources-list; files in your preferred texteditor while also
	   providing basic sanity checks.
     </para></listitem>
     </varlistentry>


   </variablelist>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1><title>Script Usage and Differences from Other APT Tools</title>
  <para>
   The &apt; commandline is designed as an end-user tool and it may
   change behavior between versions. While it tries not to break
   backward compatibility this is not guaranteed either if a change
   seems beneficial for interactive use.
  </para><para>
   All features of &apt; are available in dedicated APT tools like &apt-get;
   and &apt-cache; as well.  &apt; just changes the default value of some
   options (see &apt-conf; and specifically the Binary scope). So you should
   prefer using these commands (potentially with some additional options
   enabled) in your scripts as they keep backward compatibility as much as possible.
   </para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1><title>See Also</title>
   <para>&apt-get;, &apt-cache;, &sources-list;,
   &apt-conf;, &apt-config;,
   The APT User's guide in &guidesdir;, &apt-preferences;, the APT Howto.</para>
 </refsect1>

 <refsect1><title>Diagnostics</title>
   <para><command>apt</command> returns zero on normal operation, decimal 100 on error.</para>
 </refsect1>
 &manbugs;
</refentry>
